RG 089:032, Transportation Accountability Board
Connecticut State Library
Transportation Accountability Board records
1986-1987
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Transportation Accountability Board
5.5 cubic feet
The Transportation Accountability Board was created as an independent, non-partisan body charged with overseeing the operations of the Connecticut Department of Transportation. The Board held its first meeting on January 8, 1986 and was abolished as of July 1, 1987.
RG089_032
1988-091
Historical Note
In light of public controversies over hiring of outside consultants and the collapse of the Mianus River bridge on the Connecticut Turnpike, the Republican-controlled General Assembly enacted P.A. 85-1 during a special session in July, 1985, creating the Transportation Accountability Board as an independent, non-partisan body charged with overseeing the operations of the Connecticut Department of Transportation (DOT).
P.A. 85-1 empowered the Board to do the following: 1) Review for approval or disapproval and monitor all consultant and construction contracts entered into by DOT under the $5.6 billion Infrastructure Renewal Program (IRP); 2) Oversee implementation of an effective, on-going road and bridge maintenance program; 3) Review and approve DOT's annual plan for IRP; 4) Select and oversee the work of a management consultant, hired to review and make recommendations for improvements in DOT's organization and procedures; and 5) Issue progress reports to the Governor, the General Assembly, DOT, and other state agencies. If the Commissioner of DOT disagreed with any Board's decision regarding contracts, the law provided an appeal process to the Governor.
The law granted the Board the right to hire with available funds "such consultants, technical assistance, research and other personnel" to assist in its examinations and directed to the Board to consult with the Legislative Program Review and Investigations Committee. Members discovering that "unauthorized, illegal, or irregular" activities were being "contemplated" but had not been "consummated" were instructed to report the facts to the Governor, the Legislative Program Review Committee, and Transportation Committee of the General Assembly. Records of budgeted agencies regarding transportation matters were to be made available to the Board except in cases covered by confidentiality provisions of statutes and regulations.
The Board held its first meeting on January 8, 1986, but it was not until April 1, 1986 that an executive director and secretary were hired. Plans to add two engineers and three clerical assistants to the staff were not fully implemented in 1986. Thus, the Board operated with a reduced staff in 1986. In general, the Board held meetings approximately once a week. During 1986, the Board reviewed 106 construction contracts, rejecting only 4, and reviewed and approved all 46 consultant contracts. The final report of the management consultant hired to review the organization an operations of DOT was issued in November, 1986.
The Board operated amid charges and countercharges emanating from an atmosphere of political partisanship. In June, 1987, Governor O'Neill signed the Public Act 87-300 passed by the Democratic-controlled General Assembly abolishing the Board as of July 1, 1987.
Scope and Content
Includes meeting material, 1986-1987; and subject files, 1986-1987.
Related Material
RG 089, Dept. of Transportation, 1941-2003, bulk 1973-2003
RG 089:001, State Highway Department, 1894-1975
RG 089:010, State Boundary Line Perambulations, 1965-1997
RG 089:011, Aerial photographs, see the Research Guide to Aerial Photographs at the Connecticut State Library
RG 089:024, Connecticut Transportation Authority, 1956-1973
RG 089:030, State Traffic Commission, 1935-1995
RG 089:031, Connecticut Public Transportation Commission, 1980-2001
RG 089:037, Commissioners of Steamship Terminals, 1915
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Transportation Accountability Board
Subjects:
Connecticut. Dept. of Transportation -- Management -- Evaluation
Document Types:
Agendas; Correspondence; Minutes; Reports
Restrictions on Access
Some of these records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
These records came to the State Library the week of August 10-14, 1987.
Container List
- Series 1. Meeting material, 1986-1987
  Includes agendas, minutes and other meeting material for the Board's review.
  - 1986 January 8 - February 25 (Box 1)
  - 1986 March 4 - June 17 (Box 2)
  - 1986 June 24 - September 16 (Box 3)
  - 1986 September 23 - November 12 (Box 4)
  - 1986 November 18 - 1987 January 20 (Box 5)
  - 1987 January 27 - March 24 (Box 6)
- Series 2. Subject Files, 1986-1987
  - Appointment letters (Box 7)
  - Budget (Box 7)
  - Connecticut Society of Professional Engineers, Inc. (Box 7)
  - Copy machine research (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Connecticut transportation regulations (Box 7)
  - Dept. of Transportation organization functions and procedures - Construction (Box 7)
  - Dept. of Transportation progress reports (Box 7)
  - Emergency declarations (Box 7)
  - Equipment warranties (Box 7)
  - Equipment warranties (Box 7)
  - Ethics (Box 8)
  - Executive Director recruitment (Box 8)
  - Facilities & capital plan (Box 8)
  - Fuss & O'Neill (Box 8)
  - Guest speakers (Box 8)
  - Hartford Business Machines (Box 8)
  - Information requests/responses (Box 8)
  - Janatorial contract (Box 8)
  - Jewett City (Box 8)
  - Legislation proposed (Box 8)
  - Legislative handouts (Box 8)
  - L. O. P. C. Plimptons (Box 8)
  - Management consultant (Box 9)
  - Management consultant briefing documents (Box 9)
  - Management consultant - Draft of final report - Dept. of Transportation study - Peat Marwick (Box 9)
  - Management consultant - Final reoprt - Peat Marwick (Box 9)
  - Management consultant progress bills (Box 9)
  - Management consultant - Proposal for Dept. of Transportation study - Arthur Young (Box 9)
  - Management consultant - Proposal for Dept. of Transportation study - Peat Marwick (Box 9)
  - Management consultant R.F.P. (Box 10)
  - Management consultant selection (Box 10)
  - MBE (Minority Business Enterprise) (Box 10)
  - Media (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous supplies (Box 10)
  - Office space (Box 10)
  - P.A. 85-1 (Box 10)
  - Personal computer research (Box 10)
  - Quarterly reports (Box 10)
  - Records retention (Box 10)
  - Reimbursements (Box 11)
  - Secretary of the State filings (Box 11)
  - Selection Data General (Box 11)
  - Small business set aside (Box 11)
  - Speeches/presentations (Box 11)
  - Special meetings (Box 11)
  - Stores requisitions (Box 11)
  - Subsscriptions (Box 11)
  - Systems, Inc. (Box 11)
  - TAB (Transportation Accountability Board) (Box 11)
  - Tax exempt forms (Box 11)
  - Telecommunications (Box 11)
  - Travel authorizations (Box 11)
  - Unsigned contracts (Box 11)